最初  宇宙是一片黑暗
In the beginning, there was darkness,
紧接着一声巨响  混沌初开
and then, bang, giving birth
时间  空间和物质
to an endless, expanding existence
开始不断膨胀
of time, space and matter.
每天  我们都在解密这神秘莫测
Every day, new discoveries are unlocking the mysterious,
令人疯狂的极端之地
the mind-blowing, the deadly secrets
宇宙
of a place we call the Universe.
它是银河系领域末日终结者
It's the apocalyptic finale of our galactic neighborhood.
它也许是整个太阳系历史中
Probably the most dramatic event
最壮观的景象
in the entire history of the solar system.
我们已经知晓这颗母星
We've now uncovered sizzling clues
即将猛烈活动直至死亡
about our home star's violent demise.
这结果似乎对地球极为不利
And the outcome doesn't look good for planet Earth.
也许被热死
You could experience both death by fire
也许被冻死
and also death by ice.
新一代尖端科学发现
New cutting-edge science traces
待太阳释放出最后能量
the real horrors awaiting our planet
极度恐慌就将降临到地球上
as our Sun unleashes its final fury.
一切均将灭亡
The kiss of death for everything.
--==本影片由 CMCT 团队 荣誉出品==--
更多精彩影视 请访问 http://cmct.cc
影片压制&调校:无影  字幕来源:人人影视  招募Q号:76846146
宇
宙
太 阳 之 死
第5季　第8集
我们的太阳
Our Sun.
已经用光亮和能量孕育了我们
It's bathed us wth light and energy
45亿余年
for over 4.5 billion years.
然而像宇宙万物一样
But like all things in the cosmos,
我们的母星最终会走向灭亡
our nurturing star will eventually die.
地球也将随之逐渐消亡
And Earth could literally melt into the sunset.
当太阳光亮比现在增强一百倍时
When the Sun gets a hundred times brighter than it is now,
克雷格·德福斯特
美国西南研究院
整个地球表面将化为灰烬
the entire surface of the Earth will be incinerated.
组成陆地的岩石也将熔化
All the rock that composes the continents will melt
并汇合成为大面积熔岩
and run into seas of molten lava.
地球将不再适宜居住
The Earth will be uninhabitable.
太阳之死
The death of our Sun
对宇宙影响深远
will have a profound effect on our cosmic world.
我们依赖着母星
We rely on our home star,
它位于太阳系的中心
located in the center of our solar system.
这个巨大熔岩球体
Over one million Earths could easily fit
能够轻松装下百万余个地球
inside this gargantuan ball of bubbling gas
其内核温度达到三千万华氏度
with core temperatures reaching 30 million degrees Fahrenheit.
太阳距离我们大约九千三百万英里
The Sun is approximately 93 million miles away,
因此地球表面冷热适宜
so Earth is not too hot or too cold.
这是形成液态海水
It's the perfect distance to sustain oceans
和多样生物的完美距离
of liquid water and abundant life.
我们的生存特别依赖于
We're incredibly dependent
艾力克斯·菲利潘科
加州大学伯克利分校
太阳所提供的能量
on the Sun's energy for our survival.
首先  植物利用阳光
First and foremost, plants utilize solar energy
进行光合作用  才能够生长
in photosynthesis so that they can grow.
然后我们利用植物获取食物
And then, we use plants for food
其他动物也是如此
and so do other animals,
我们也食用那些动物的肉
And we eat those other animals.
我们还使用由腐烂植物
We also use the fossil fuels
转变来的矿物燃料
from partially decayed plants.
风能也是由太阳热量产生的
Winds are also generated by the Sun's heat.
我们随处都在利用太阳能量
We're using solar energy everywhere.
所有这些赋予生命的热能和光能
All this life-giving heat and light
都来自于太阳内核
comes from the Sun's core,
这里就像个巨大的核反应堆
a colossal nuclear reactor comprised of
四分之三是氢气  余下为氦气
three-quarters hydrogen and the rest mostly helium
还有少量重元素
with traces of heavier elements.
在这里  氢原子核组合形成氦原子核
Here, hydrogen nuclei combine to form helium nuclei.
这个过程称为聚变  能够释放辐射能量
This process called fusion gives off radiant energy.
这辆车就好比刚生成时的恒星太阳
This car is like a newly formed star like the Sun.
当太阳诞生时
When a star like the Sun is born,
随之诞生的还有一整箱油
it's born with a full tank of gas.
如果我将油箱灌满
So if I fill this tank with gas,
就像氢元素被吸引到一起
that's like the hydrogen coming together gravitationally,
组成一个炙热高密度内核
forming a hot, dense core.
油继而燃烧
That gas will later burn.
在恒星中
In the case of a star,
氢元素将融合组成氦元素
hydrogen will fuse to form helium,
向恒星供给能量
giving the star energy.
就像油在车里燃烧
Just as in the case of the gas burning in the car,
将提供车运动所需能量
that'll give the car energy with which to move.
就像一辆汽车
Like an automobile,
太阳也会耗尽燃料
the Sun will eventually run out of fuel,
地球也将失去这个赖以生存的能量之源
and Earth will be without this crucial power source.
氢元素聚合生成氦元素的不对称比例
The rate at which it's fusing hydrogen into helium,
最终会导致内核中氢元素耗尽
it will someday simply run out of hydrogen in its core.
这可以借鉴其他类似星体
We can see other similar stars
它们诞生时间早于太阳
that were born much earlier than the Sun,
现在已经逐渐消亡
and they're now dying.
为了追踪太阳之死
To track our Sun's dark future,
我们回到了它诞生之时
we travel back in time to its beginning.
这些奇异的气体云雾被称做星云
These exotic clouds of gas and dust are called nebulas.
由正在消亡的天体残余物组成
They consist of the remnants of dying stars.
但根据最新研究
But upon closer observation,
它们是孕育
they're actually stellar nurseries
恒星的温床
where stars like our Sun were born.
大约四十五亿年前的银河系中
About 4 1/2 billion years ago in our galaxy,
道格·邓肯
科罗拉多大学
一团巨大的气体云雾
a giant cloud of gas and dust
在引力的作用下逐渐聚集起来
gradually was pulled together by gravity.
当引力作用使得星云崩溃时
And as gravity caused that cloud to collapse,
大量能量释放出来
a lot of energy was released,
中心地带急速升温
it heated up and finally, in the center,
核反应开始促使氢元素转变为氦元素
nuclear reaction started changing hydrogen into helium
一颗新星就这样诞生了
and a new star was born.
余下的星际物质围绕新生太阳转动
The remaining stellar material swirled around the newborn Sun.
发生碰撞并接合在一起
It collided and coalesced,
最终形成太阳系的八个星球
eventually sculpting the eight planets
同时包括地球
in our solar system including Earth.
当时  星风开始将
When that happened, a stellar wind turned on
所有其他物质清理干净
and cleared out all the extra material
只留下了我们现在所知的星球
leaving the planets that we have today
和其他一些天体
and additional bodies,
其中有些发生碰撞或与其他星球融为一体
some of which collided or merged with the other planets.
在宇宙无数的发光源之中
Among the billions of points of light in the universe,
我们的太阳只是一个普通的天体
our Sun is an average star.
还有比它大一百倍的天体
There are stars 100 times its mass.
太阳真实的颜色
And contrary to its appearance,
与日升日落时呈现的颜色
the true color of the Sun
大不相同
differs from what we see when it rises and sets.
太阳其实是个白色天体  并非黄色
The Sun is actually a white star, not a yellow star.
白得像这辆车
It's white like this car.
光谱的峰值
Now, it's true that the peak of its spectrum
是黄色光波
is sort of in the yellow region,
但也发出一些蓝光和绿光
but it also emits some blue light and green light,
还有橙色  红色光
and orange and red.
所有这些颜色聚集在一起
And all those colors together
被我们的视网膜和大脑所接收
are perceived by our retina and our brain
就成为白色
as the color white.
太阳和我们人类有很多共同之处
Our Sun has a lot in common with humans.
当它年轻时
When it was young,
十分活跃毫无规律
it was extremely active and often unpredictable.
我们发现它真是惊奇之物
What we found was really very surprising.
当类似太阳的天体
We found that stars like the Sun,
在年轻时
when they're very young,
转速比现在快很多
Are rotating much, much faster than today.
想象一颗飞速旋转
If you can imagine something as big as the Sun
自转周期只有一天或者更短的太阳
just whipping around in one day or even less,
那可就大不一样了
that was a very different kind of Sun.
上面会发生各种爆炸与喷发
It's having all kinds of eruptions
不断地向地球发射出粒子
that blasted particles through space that hit the Earth.
但是如今  我们的太阳只是中年寿命
Right now, our Sun is middle-aged
运行平和  规律而稳定
and has settled into a quieter, regular schedule.
同时仍然释放着能量
But it's still generating a lot of energy.
如今的太阳  已经45亿岁
The Sun, right now, is about 4 1/2 billion years old.
几乎达到
It's slightly under
其既定寿命的一半
half of its total anticipated lifetime.
就好像是这辆车
So it's kind of like this car
油箱里的油即将消耗一半
with a little bit more than half of its tank still full.
太阳以稳定然剧烈的速率
The Sun now is burning fuel...
消耗燃料
that is, fusing hydrogen to helium...
即氢氦核聚变
at a steady but ferocious rate.
这就好像是一颗900亿吨级的炸弹
It's like a 90 billion megaton bomb
接二连三不间歇地爆炸
going off every second.
真是强大得不可思议
It's just an incredible amount of power.
身居地球  事实上
On Earth, we're actually only receiving
我们只接收到了
about one 2-billionth of the energy
太阳产生的能量的五亿分之一
that's being produced at the Sun.
以我们如今的科技水平
Now, on a daily basis, that's enough energy to power
霍莉·吉尔伯特
国家航空航天局戈达航天中心
这足以支持2.9亿亿颗100瓦的灯泡
about 29 million billion
同时点亮一小时
100-watt light bulbs for one hour.
从太阳内部产生的能量
The amount of energy being generated
实在是巨大得难以计量
in the interior of the Sun is just enormous.
太阳将持续这种活动
Our Sun will continue
生产能量  并如此穷尽毕生
to churn out energy over its entire lifetime,
据估算  也就是还有120亿年
which is estimated to be around 12 billion years.
二十世纪九十年代  科学家们通过测算
In the 1990s, scientists confirmed its age
太阳的亮度和初始质量
and when it will die
同时对其声波进行分析
by measuring its brightness and original mass
得出了它的年龄与确切死期
as well as analyzing its sound waves.
光线是无法通过太阳的
Light doesn't penetrate the Sun.
因为它不透明
It's opaque.
这听上去很奇怪  因为光线正是来自于太阳
That sounds strange because light comes from the Sun,
却无法穿过它
but light can't pass through it.
因此直到近些年
So until recently, there was no way
我们才找到办法侦测太阳内部的深层地带
to probe the deep interior of the Sun.
是种被称为的太阳地震学的科学
There's a science now called helioseismology
利用声波
that uses sound waves to actually probe
侦测太阳内部结构
the interior structure of the Sun.
我们因而才弄清楚
And so we have a very good knowledge
太阳的内部结构
of what the interior structure of the star looks like,
并且得以缩小范围和最终确定
and that's allowed us to constrain and confirm
太阳的准确年龄与进化过程
the models of the Sun's age and its evolution.
奇怪的是  太阳比初生时亮度增加了30%
Strangely, our Sun is now 30% brighter than it was at birth.
随着年岁的增长
As it ages,
还将变得更加明亮和强大
it will gradually grow even brighter and more powerful.
地球上的气候对太阳能量的波动非常敏感
Our climate is very sensitive to the energy from the Sun.
因此  如果你仍在操心人类的所作所为
So if you're worried about global warming,
对全球变暖的激烈影响
you worry about what humans are doing to the atmosphere,
同时也要明白
but you also need to know
太阳也在干扰大气层
what the Sun is doing to the atmosphere.
最新的估测结果指出
The most recent estimate says that maybe 20%
全球变暖20%的热量
of all the warming that's happening,
取决于太阳
the global warming, is due to the Sun.
十亿年后  地球表面能见度
In one-billion years, our star's luminosity
将增强10%
will be 10% greater
温度也将上升100度
and temperatures on our planet will be 100 degrees hotter.
空气中的水分
The moisture in the air
很好的吸收了红外线与热量
is very good at trapping infrared radiation or heat.
就好像是给地球裹上了一层毛毯
And so it's sort of like putting a blanket on the Earth.
由此带来的恶劣影响是这样的
Now, here is the bad part.
随着地球变暖
As the Earth warms up,
海洋将加剧蒸发
the oceans evaporate even more,
导致更多的热量被锁定
we trap more heat
然后地球会加剧变暖
and so the Earth warms up more.
然后当地球变暖加剧  再一次
And when the Earth warms up more, again,
更多的热量被锁定  恶性循环  循循不息
we trap even more heat and the effect can run away.
这就是温室效应
It's what we call the Greenhouse Effect.
脱缰的温室效应导致的气温飙升
With this surge of heat due to the runaway Greenhouse Effect,
关系地球上生物的生死存亡
life on Earth will be in peril.
届时  所有的生物群
Whole societies will need to retreat
将只好退避到地下遮蔽处
to underground shelters during the day,
只有在夜晚气温降下的时候  才能走上地面
then emerge at night when the temperature cools down.
然而随着温度不断攀升
But as the thermometer continues to climb,
终将无处可藏身
there eventually will be nowhere to run or hide.
最终的结果是已知的
We know how that story ends.
那就是  金星
It's called the planet Venus.
想想看
If you think about it,
金星距离太阳只比地日距离短30%
Venus is only about 30% closer to the Sun than the Earth is,
但是却热上很多  温度高达800度
but it's way, way, way hotter, 800 degrees.
目前我们还没有掌握
We don't quite have the technology that would allow us
能够在金星表面生存的技术
to survive on the surface of Venus,
但是可以推断
but we could imagine what would be required,
隔热是必要前提
insulating yourself from the heat.
这将是个巨大挑战
So it would be a challenge.
30亿年后
In 3 billion years,
太阳的亮度会增加40%
our Sun's brightness sill increase 40%.
至那时  海洋将被烤干
By this time, oceans will have boiled off.
地球变成沙漠之球
Earth will have become a global desert.
太阳会因氢氦核聚变
The Sun will have used up about three-quarters
耗尽内部四分之三的氢
of the hydrogen in its core fused to helium,
就好像这辆车  已经消耗了四分之三的燃油
like this car is three-quarters empty.
届时  太阳会比如今明亮
By this time, the Sun will be brighter
并且体积也更大
than it is now and bigger.
因此  地球会变得更热
So Earth will be hotter.
而不再是生命的乐土
It won't be a nice place to live at that time.
然而噩梦还远没有结束
And the solar nightmare is far from over.
当太阳寿命超过100亿岁
As the Sun nears its ten billionth birthday and beyond,
将发生终极质变
the most drastic changes will occur.
当太阳覆盖了整个地平线
If human-type civilizations are still around,
如若人类文化仍在
what will be the options for survival
将何去何从
when our Sun eventually fills the entire horizon?
结局是注定的
It's a foregone conclusion.
当太阳达到100亿岁寿命的时候
When the Sun is about 10 billion years old,
会耗尽内部所有的氢燃料
it will run out of hydrogen fuel in its core.
也就吹响了这颗恒星的死亡号角
It's the beginning of the end for our star,
并且  它不会静静地死去
and it won't die peacefully.
对地球来说  全球变暖以及其他的各种灾祸
As for Earth, global warming or other cataclysms
仅仅10亿年后就将灭绝所有生物
could snuff out every living thing in a mere 1 billion years.
就算那时  人类的后代找到了生存的方法
But if human descendants somehow manage to survive until then,
他们面对的也是人间炼狱
they could face a living hell.
当太阳耗尽内核所有的氢
When the Sun burns through all of its hydrogen at its core,
就会开始紧缩
it will eventually start contracting on itself,
霍莉·吉尔伯特
国家航空航天局戈达航天中心
因为一旦氢的燃烧停止
because it's no longer burning through the hydrogen,
核聚变也将停止
fusing it together,
能够与万有引力抗衡的放射压也会停止生成
creating this radiation pressure outwards
内缩的力便胜过了外扩的力
to balance the gravitational pull inwards.
当太阳内核的氢聚变停止
While hydrogen fusion will stop in the core,
地壳的氢聚变将接过接力棒
it will continue to fuse at a faster rate
以更高的速率进行
in the shell surrounding the core.
多余的能量扩大太阳的外层
The extra energy will expand the outer layers of the Sun.
这意味着太阳将变得
That'll mean that the Sun will grow
更加能量十足  光亮耀眼
much more powerful, much more luminous,
艾力克斯·菲利潘科
加州大学伯克利分校
因为太阳的内核收缩速率
Because the hydrogen shell will be fusing
会比往常快很多
while the core is contracting
因此氢壳将被熔化
at a greater rate than it normally would.
氢壳熔化产生的能量
All the pressure from the energy generated
会生成压强
in this hydrogen-fusing Shell
而压强将使得太阳外部结构的膨胀
will cause the outer parts of the Sun to expand,
从而使太阳成为一颗红巨星
Making it into a red giant.
红巨星指的是一颗恒星已经
A red giant is a star that has exhausted
耗尽了其内部核心最初储备的氢能源
the primary reservoir of hydrogen fuel at its core,
留下了正在形成的高浓度氦
leaving behind a buildup of the heavier, denser helium.
一颗和太阳大小相似的恒星
An average-sized star like our Sun will spend
会以红巨星的身份度过最后的二十亿年
the final 2 billion years of its life as a red giant.
我们之所以称其为红巨星
We call it a red giant
是因为当恒星发生膨胀时
because as this expansion happens,
其表面积会增大很多
the surface area gets so great
表面温度也会降低
that it actually cools off and,
从温度的角度上说
in terms of temperature,
恒星表面温度越低颜色就会越红
stars that are cooler appear redder.
在红巨星最初的形成阶段
During the initial red giant phase,
会有灾难性的变化发生
catastrophic changes will occur.
我们的太阳将会膨胀到
Our Sun will swell to 20 to 30 times
其原始体积的二十到三十倍
its original size
光照强度将会是现在的一百倍
and become one-hundred times more luminous.
当太阳红巨星膨胀时
As our red giant Sun expands,
在相对静止的氦核周围
it will continue to vigorously fuse hydrogen
将持续猛烈的和氢气熔合
in the shell surrounding the inactive helium core,
从而在核中制造出更多的氦气
thus producing more helium in the core.
一旦一切真的发生
As that happens,
太阳的核心将会进一步瓦解  温度会更高
the core of the Sun collapses further and gets hotter,
太阳会在几十亿年间
and the Sun gradually expands
逐步的膨胀
over the course of a couple of billion years.
事实上  太阳核心的温度
Eventually, the core of the Sun is
克雷格·德福斯特
西南研究院
已经足够燃烧氦气了
hot enough to ignite the helium.
这被称为氦闪
You get what's called a helium flash.
就如同点燃燃气烤架时
It's like the stellar equivalent of the big woof
一声扑哧的巨响
when you light a gas barbecue.
被点燃的氦气温度已经足够进行熔合
The ignited helium will be hot enough to undergo fusion,
从而在核内产生了碳和氧
now creating carbon and oxygen in the core.
即将陨落的太阳又能从
The dying Sun will be resuscitated
短暂的新能量中得到恢复
with this new but temporary form of energy.
我被困在沙漠里并且汽车没油了
I'm stuck here in the desert, and I've run out of gas.
但是我在后备箱存有一加仑备用油
But, you know, I have a spare gallon here in the trunk,
如果我把油倒进油箱
and if I pour this gas into the gas tank,
那么这辆车又能行驶很长一段路
that'll allow the car to keep going for a while longer.
这和太阳是同一个道理
This is kinda similar to the Sun.
在红巨星阶段
During the red giant stage,
太阳将把氢能源消耗殆尽
It's gonna run out of hydrogen as fuel,
但是它将在数千万年内
but it'll have helium that can briefly
产生氦能源
for a few tens of millions of years,
熔合之后生成的碳和氧
fuse to carbon and oxygen,
又将为太阳提供新的能源
providing a new source of energy
使它能够继续运转很长一段时间
that'll keep the Sun going for a while longer.
在红巨星初始阶段结束时
At the end of the initial red giant phase,
陨落的太阳会进入一个稳定的氦燃烧阶段
the dying Sun will enter this stable helium-burning phase.
它的温度将更高  体积会缩小
It will become hotter yet somewhat smaller.
但这仅仅只是暴风雨来临前的平静罢了
But this is merely a lull before the storm.
因为太阳进入的红巨星时期
This is because the Sun's transition to
被分为两个阶段
a red giant actually comes in two phases.
当其处于第二阶段后
During the second phase,
核内的氦气将被耗尽
the helium will be exhausted in the core,
而太阳的核将由碳和氧组成
which will now consist of carbon and oxygen.
此核将重新收缩和加热
The core will again start to contract and heat up.
但是氦气在太阳的外壳中仍有剩余
But helium will still exist in the Shell,
它会继续熔合
and it will continue to fuse,
在收缩的核中制造更多的碳和氧
forming more carbon and oxygen in the contracting core
而这一切将被
and all of this will still be surrounded
氢壳包裹住
by the hydrogen shell
并继续和氦气熔合
That's still fusing to helium.
当太阳成为红巨星之后
When the Sun becomes a red giant,
会膨胀开来
It will expand out
它将做的第一件事就是
and the first thing it'll do is
吞食水星
engulf the planet Mercury
事实上是燃烧它
and eventually incinerate it,
使水星蒸发  完全吞食它
evaporate it, eat it up.
接下来太阳会向金星膨胀
Then it'll expand out to Venus.
在氦气转变为碳
After the helium changing into carbon
道格·邓肯
科罗拉多大学
并耗尽所有能量后
uses up all of its energy,
其内核将再次收缩
then the core begins to shrink a second time,
太阳外部再次膨胀
The outer part expands a second time,
然后开始变得极不稳定
and it's not very stable.
当太阳红巨星处于第二阶段时
During the second red giant phase,
剧烈的收缩和膨胀
The wild contraction and expansion
会使太阳变得像一个缓慢跳动的心脏
will make our Sun pulsate like a slow-beating heart.
跳动会在每几百或几千年就发生一次
The pulsations can occur every few hundred or thousand years.
每一次的跳动
and with each pulsation,
都会使整个行星系统一片混乱
planetary pandemonium will ensue.
水星和金星都难逃厄运
Mercury and Venus are doomed.
它们都将被红巨星吞食
They'll be engulfed by the red giant.
但是  在很多的科学文献中
However, there's been some debate
也存在争议
in the scientific literature
地球是否真的会被吞食
as to whether the Earth would actually be engulfed or not.
巨大的太阳是足够吞食地球的
The Sun will be large enough to engulf the Earth.
地球的生死未卜
Earth's future is uncertain
因为地球就在存在于灭亡
Because it lies on the borderline
之间的界线之上
between being engulfed and surviving.
但是现在也有宇航员
But astronomers now have one possible sneak
对地球的最终命运有一个恰当的预言
preview of our planet's ultimate fate.
红外线光学望远镜捕捉到了
The infrared optical telescope array has captured
一颗垂死恒星  天鹅座-X的特写镜头
close-up photos of a death star, Chi Cygni,
它离地球约有五十光年
which is approximately 50 light-years from Earth.
天鹅座-X已经处于红巨星阶段的末尾了
Chi Cygni is near the end of its red giant stage,
当它膨胀的足够大
When it's grown really big.
在其存在的几百万年间
and in those last few million years of existence,
会开始有规律的跳动
It starts pulsating.
事实上  它每四百年跳动一次
It actually pulsates every 400 years or so,
膨胀之后变得又大又亮
Getting bigger and brighter
收缩之后变得又小又暗
and smaller and fainter.
如果这个巨大膨胀的天鹅座-X
If the massively bloated star
是我们的太阳的话
Chi Cygni were our Sun,
它将一直吞没每一颗行星直到火星
It would have consumed every planet out to Mars.
地球以及地球上所有的生命
Earth and all its wondrous forms of life
将被垂死之星
would have been melded with
内部的物质所熔合
the materials inside the dying star.
我们的生命显然很短暂
We obviously haven't been around long enough,
在我们有生之年看不到这些
and will not be in our lifetimes,
所以很难确切的知道
to understand exactly what's gonna happen
太阳的陨落到底会发生什么
when the Sun dies.
所以我们只有通过对其他恒星的观察
So we need to look to other stars
来举一反三
in order to see how that might work.
我们通过对其他垂死之星的观察
Observations of other death stars
看到了太阳的长远的未来
have offered a startling glimpse
这使我们感到惊讶
at our own Sun's long-term prognosis
还有什么会在太阳系中被留存下来
and what's in store for the rest of the solar system.
地球将会掉进一个炙热的无底洞
Earth could be catapulted into the fiery abyss.
但是  最新的一项研究表明
However, recent research indicates
在宇宙特定状况下
that with the right set of cosmic conditions,
我们脆弱的星球一定可以逃离厄运
a shockingly different fate may await our fragile planet.
一切都将会有终结
All things must end.
在五十亿年后
In about 5 billion years,
我们挚爱的太阳将不再滋润大地
Our motherly Sun will stop
为万物带来生机
nurturing its planetary offspring.
它开始在死亡之中挣扎
As it begins an agonizing death March,
膨胀一百倍
it will expand 100-fold and devour
先将水星吞没  然后是金星
the planets Mercury and then Venus.
在临近红巨星第二阶段末尾时
Near the end of its second red giant phase,
太阳会收缩和膨胀数次
the Sun will contract and expand several times.
每一次的收缩和膨胀
With each pulsation,
使地球离这颗濒死恒星更近
our dying star will become dangerously close
随时有被卷入的危险
to swallowing Earth.
然而  在特定的条件下
However, with the right set of circumstances,
地球有可能幸免于难
our planet could be spared.
太阳持续不断地形成的太阳风
There's a phenomenon called the solar wind that's continuously blowing,
克雷格·德福斯特
西南研究院
带动太阳大气外层的物质
lifting material from the outer layers of the Sun's atmosphere
并将它们释放到星际空间
out into interstellar space.
当太阳进入膨胀的红巨星阶段后
When the Sun begins to expand into the red giant phase,
其大气外层比现在的大气更为离散
the outer layers of its atmosphere are even more loosely bound than they are now.
这样一来太阳风影响范围会更大
And so the solar wind will be much more prominent.
研究数据标明如果太阳风带走
The data indicate that if the solar wind blows off
太阳质量的百分之三十
about 30% of the Sun's mass,
太阳对地球的引力就会减弱
its gravitational pull will weaken enough to allow Earth
这足以使地球向外围移动
to move sufficiently outward.
如果太阳的质量减少了
If the Sun loses some of its mass,
其引力会变弱
its gravity gets weaker and
地球公转轨道也因而扩大
the Earth's orbit is gonna get bigger.
道格·邓肯
科罗拉多大学
如果我们运气够好
So if we're lucky,
地球的轨道会扩大到太阳的膨胀范围以外
our orbit will expand out enough that it will miss the expanding Sun
从而逃过被燃为灰烬的命运
and we won't get incinerated.
然而地球无法完全绕开危险
But Earth won't be completely removed from harm's way.
太阳在减少质量的同时
While the Sun might lose mass,
与地球之间也会产生潮汐作用力
it could also have a tidal interaction with our planet,
这同样会导致地球被炙烤
and this could have sizzling consequences.
该过程中至少存在两种此消彼长的影响力
There are at least two competing effects.
艾力克斯·菲利潘科
加州大学伯克利分校
尽管随着太阳步入老龄阶段
Although as the Sun ages,
其质量会减少
it's losing mass...
也就是说地球的轨道会逐渐远离太阳
and that means that Earth's orbit gradually drifts away from the Sun,
但实际上由于地球离太阳表面过近
it's also true that Earth, being pretty close to the surface of the Sun,
会使太阳上掀起一波波气浪
will raise a tide, a bulge of gas on the Sun.
而气浪和地球之间的引力相互作用
And a gravitational interaction between that bulge
会减慢地球的公转速度
and the Earth will actually slow down the Earth in its orbit,
从而使地球逐渐向轨道内侧旋转
causing the Earth to gradually spiral in.
太阳质量的减少可能使地球轨道安全外移
So maybe the loss of mass will move us out enough to be safe.
但产生的潮汐力可能把地球向内牵引
But maybe the tidal forces will spiral us in enough
以致地球可能被太阳吞没并燃为灰烬
that we'll be engulfed and the Earth will be incinerated.
等五六十亿年后再回来看
And if you come back in 5 or 6 billion years,
就能知道鹿死谁手了
you'll know which one wins out.
地球可能是幸运的
Earth just might get lucky.
一个国际天文学家小组发现了太阳系外的
An international team of astronomers discovered a planet
一颗行星逃过了其主星死亡带来的厄运
outside our solar system that survived the death of its home star.
这颗系外行星的体积至少是木星的三倍
The exoplanet is at least three times as massive as Jupiter
并绕着恒星391佩贾斯公转
and orbits the star dubbed 391 Pegasi,
该恒星与太阳体积相当
which is about the same mass as our Sun.
有些系外行星经历了
Some exoplanets clearly do survive
其主星的红巨星阶段后仍能存在
through the red giant stage.
比如391佩贾斯与其系外行星
For example, 391 Pegasi is a star that has an exoplanet around it,
绕着它公转的这颗行星幸存了下来
a planet orbiting it, and that planet is still there.
这颗行星可能和地球一样有岩石核心
Now, it might have a rocky Earth-like core
甚至有铁质内核
and perhaps even an iron central region.
但我们认为它很可能是气态或液态行星
But we think it's mostly gaseous and liquid.
391佩贾斯及其巨大的气体行星
391 Pegasi and its gas giant planet
之间的轨道距离和
have a similar orbital distance from each other
地球与太阳之间的轨道距离非常相似
as Earth does from our Sun,
即约为九千万英里
which is about 90 million miles.
天文学家们认为这颗系外行星能存活
Astronomers think the exoplanet survived
是因为已死亡的主星质量的减少
because its death star lost mass,
导致对该行星的引力作用的减弱
which reduced its gravitational pull on the planet,
其程度恰好使行星稍微向外偏离
just enough so that it drifted slightly outward.
这些绕391佩贾斯公转的行星
The planets around 391 Pegasi is likely to be one of these planets
布拉德·海森
加州大学洛城分校
在向外旋转和在被潮汐力作用向内牵引
that sort of walked the knife edge between
之间找到了微妙的平衡点
spiraling outwards and being dragged in by tides.
但与主星距离恰到好处的行星
But you would not expect to find a lot of planets
并不多见
in that particular range of distances.
大多数行星要么被主星完全吞没
You would expect them to either be completely swallowed
要么就远远地移开
or have them be much further out.
因此只有这两种力达到微妙的平衡
So it requires a somewhat delicate balance of the two competing forces
才能使行星移动到安全范围
to actually enable a planet to survive at that sort of location.
由此看来  行星的幸存已有先例
So there's one case in which the planet survived.
但不幸的是在这类似太阳系的星系里
The bad news is that in this solar system,
该行星的体积比木星的还要大
the planet is really big, larger than Jupiter.
因此它的幸存几率要比
And so it probably has a better chance of surviving
地球这样的小行星大得多
than a small planet like the Earth would.
391佩贾斯产生的恒星风
It appears that stellar winds
和热力脉冲似乎
and thermal pulsations produced by 391 Pegasi
使系外行星的大气表层物质在引力作用下
pulled atmospheric material from the outer layers of the exoplanet
被释放到太空中
and hurled it into space.
然而这颗气体巨星仍幸存了下来
However, the gas giant planet survived
因所散失的质量在其可承受范围之内
because it could afford to lose a lot of mass.
可推测该行星所散失物质的质量
We can speculate that it may have lost
相当于不止一个地球
one or more Earth masses of material.
很显然  如果地球散失了相当的质量
And of course, if the Earth lost that much material,
也就不复存在了
it wouldn't be here.
当然  与木星等大的气体巨星
Certainly, a Jupiter-sized planet, a gas giant
并不适合人类居住
isn't inhabitable by people.
但令人感兴趣的是当太阳进入红巨星阶段
But it's still intriguing that if the Sun went to the red giant phase,
木星将可能是幸存下来的行星
it's possible that Jupiter would survive.
绕391佩贾斯公转的气体巨星
The continued existence of the gas giant planet
的存在无论如何都不能有力地说明
orbiting 391 Pegasi doesn't provide conclusive evidence one way or the other,
地球能否在太阳的死亡后幸存下来
whether Earth will survive the death of our Sun.
但可以肯定的是
But one thing seems certain.
早在太阳成为红巨星之前
Long before our Sun becomes a red giant,
我们的星球已不再适合地球生命的生存
our planet will no longer be hospitable for Earth-type life.
未来的文明都必须在人间炼狱
Any future civilizations will need to relocate,
形成前数十亿年迁徙到其他星球
and billions of years before the impending inferno.
今后大约十亿年的时间里
About a billion years from now,
假如你们还活着  我建议你们移居火星
if viewers were around, I'd recommend that you move to Mars.
那时火星已经不像现在这么冷了
Mars, instead of being too cool like it is now,
那里的气温可能会更为适宜
would probably have a somewhat more favorable temperature.
如果火星地底有水
If there is water underground in Mars,
且我们掌握了现在仍未知的某种技术
and we don't really know one way or the other for certain yet,
你们就可以好好利用这些水
maybe you could use some of that water
并在火星上安享晚年了
and you might have a comfortable retirement on the planet Mars.
要移居火星并非易事
But the move to Mars wouldn't be simple.
未来这颗红色行星虽会比现在更为温暖
The red planet would be warmer than it is today,
却仍缺少某些生命的必要元素
but it would still be missing a few of life's necessities.
首先要创造适宜的大气环境
You have to create an atmosphere.
接下来要制造足够的压力
You have to have pretty high pressures in order to
以使地面上形成液态水
have molten water on the surface.
还要制造氧气
You need to somehow generate oxygen.
我们说某颗行星或卫星是人类的可居住区
Just because a planet or a moon is in the habitable zone
并不代表它们已可供居住
doesn't mean that it's already habitable.
如果你是名策略规划师
If you were a strategic planner,
你可能会设想十亿年后
you would encourage the growth of plant life on Mars
在火星上种植植物
a billion years in the future.
以此制造氧气
You would generate oxygen,
使火星更适合人类居住
and you'd make that planet more hospitable for us.
也许稍微自负点说  我们称之为地球化
Perhaps, a little egotistically, we call that terraforming,
我们能够创造出另一个类似地球的行星
That we could form another planet in the shape of Terra or the Earth.
我希望我们可以着手于此
I hope we're here to do that.
即使高度文明的社会成功殖民到火星上
Even if an advanced society manages to colonize Mars,
这个新家也只会是暂时的
This new home will be temporary.
适合居住区
太阳会继续变得更大更亮
The Sun will continue to become brighter and bigger,
将宜居地带不断向外推出
Pushing the habitable zone ever farther out.
在红巨星阶段
During the red giant phase,
地球人又得搬家了
Earthlings will have to move again,
也许搬到木星或者土星某个含水量多的卫星上
Perhaps to the water-rich moons of Jupiter or Saturn,
但每到一个新地方
But with every new location,
都将遇到更多的艰难险阻
There will be more obstacles.
到太阳的红巨星阶段临近结束时
Near the end of the Sun's red giant stage,
它会急剧变大变亮
It will rapidly be growing much brighter and much bigger
所以我们搬到新的宜居带将更为频繁
So we'll need to move to the new habitable zone much more frequently.
搬到一个新的行星或卫星上的另一个问题是
Another problem with moving to a new planet or a moon
运送所有人浪费的财力以及
Is that it would be very difficult
遇到的困难都将会是巨大的
and expensive to move all humans.
那么你会怎么选择
So whom do you choose?
只运送一些社会的精英吗
Just some elite subset of society?
那会造成更大的问题
That would create great problems.
除了在太阳成为红巨星前遗弃地球之外
Instead of abandoning Earth before the Sun becomes a red giant,
另一个选择是移动地球
Another alternative might be to actually move the entire planet.
这可能听起来有点像科幻小说
This may sound like science fiction,
但相关的技术已经被考虑到了
But technologies are already being considered
有可能将地球从太阳的灾难中拯救出来
That might rescue Earth from the solar apocalypse.
太阳将会灭亡的预测已经被广泛接受
Predictions about our Sun's demise are widely accepted.
在大约五十亿年后
In about 5 billion years,
太阳将会开始漫长的剧烈的死亡期
our star will begin a long, violent death.
当它迅速成为红巨星时
As it mushrooms into a red giant,
它会湮没水星金星以及很有可能地球
It will vaporize planets Mercury, Venus and most likely Earth.
如果人类文明仍然存在
If human-type civilizations still exist,
他们肯定已经搬到了太阳系之外
They will have already relocated to the outer solar system.
他们甚至可能连地球也一起搬出来了
And they may have even hauled Earth away with them.
难题是要找到恰当的宇宙推车
The challenge will be finding the right cosmic moving van.
我们有可能慢慢移动地球
We might gradually move the Earth
到一个新的宜居带  比如说通过
To a new habitable zone by, for example,
艾力克斯·菲利潘科
加州大学伯克利分校
将一颗小行星带到某个轨道上
taking an asteroid and bringing it into an orbit
好让它能每隔一段时间
so that it comes reasonably close to the Earth
靠近地球并给地球一个向外移动的力
every once in a while and gives it a gravitational tug outward.
现在科学家正在进行电脑模拟
Right now, scientists are running computer simulations
来论证用人工或无人驾驶的火箭
to test the feasibility of actually moving Earth
移动地球的可能性
using manned or drone rockets.
为了实现那个
In order to do that,
我们也许得用太阳帆
We would either have to use solar sails, perhaps,
霍莉·吉尔伯特
国家航空航天局戈达航天中心
来引导小行星进入正确的轨道
to direct this asteroid into the correct place,
或者用混合燃料的火箭
or maybe a fusion-powered rocket.
在十亿年之后我们可能拥有其他技术
In a billion years we may have other technologies that, you know,
可以更容易做到
are much easier...
谁知道到时候我们能做什么呢
and who knows what we can do by then.
研究表明小行星在太阳成为红巨星前
Researchers have determined that an asteroid
必须每隔六千年
would need to be rounded up every 6,000 years
将地球向外拉一次
to keep nudging our planet outward as our Sun grows in brightness.
如果它很慢很平稳地拉地球
If it does that very gradually, very steadily,
超过好几百万年
but over millions of years,
那我们就会逐渐移动出来
Then we will gradually drift out,
与宜居带的扩张保持同步
keeping pace with the drifting habitable zone.
就算地球能在危险带以外继续绕太阳运行
Even if Earth could be re-orbited beyond the danger zone,
未来的阳光也是阴暗的
its future remains bleak.
到红巨星第二阶段末尾
Near the end of the second red giant phase,
太阳的剧烈运动将会停息
the unstable pulsations of our Sun will subside
因为它的大部分外层大气物质已经喷射出去
Because much of its outer atmosphere will be ejecting away.
然后这意外着它的能量将会逐渐枯竭
However, this means its energy will be rapidly depleting.
太阳质量不会那么大了
There won't be as much mass,
因为巨大的引力挤压稀薄的氦气层
as much gravity pushing down on the thin helium layer
并将其压缩
and compressing it,
它就不会像之前一样对温度如此敏感了
And it won't be as sensitive to the temperature.
在这个阶段  太阳实际上变得更小
At this stage, the Sun will actually become smaller
更热更蓝  而不是不断向外膨胀的红巨星
and hotter and bluer, not red and big and extended.
所以核反应频率将会下降
And so the nuclear reaction rates are going down.
最终  当恒星是去足够的质量后
So eventually, when the star has lost enough mass,
布拉德·海森
加州大学洛城分校
那些核反应就基本消失了
Those reaction rates basically die away.
所以该恒星  这里是太阳
So the star, in this case the Sun,
将最终能源耗竭
will eventually run out of fuel
并开始收缩
and it will start to shrink.
不像其他恒星
Unlike other stars,
当太阳能源耗竭时
our dying Sun will not go out with a bang
不会发生爆炸
when it runs out of fuel.
有些恒星死亡时会产生超新星爆炸
Some death stars actually produce a supernova explosion,
爆炸的光会瞬时照亮整个星系
a burst of radiation that can temporarily outshine an entire galaxy.
但为什么我们的太阳
But why won't our Sun
死亡时不会有如此绚丽呢
have a spectacular fireworks display upon its death?
这正是某个观众想要问的
That's what one viewer wanted to ask the universe,
来自罗德岛纽波特的里洛伊·G发信息给我们
so Leroy G. From Newport, Rhode island, texted us
为什么太阳死亡时不会发生超新星爆炸
里洛伊  我很高兴地确信太阳
Leroy, I'm sure glad the Sun
不会发生超新星爆炸
won't explode as a supernova.
有两点理由
There's two reasons.
首先  太阳质量不足以产生爆炸
First, the Sun isn't massive enough to explode on its own.
恒星必须要有太阳的八至十倍
Stars have to be 8 or 10 times
的质量才能发生爆炸
The mass of the Sun to explode on their own.
另外  太阳没有伴星供它
And second, the Sun doesn't have a companion star
获得物质  增大质量
from which it could steal material, grow in mass,
最终变得不稳定并爆炸
and eventually become unstable and explode.
在太阳生命的最后阶段  它的外层大气
At the last stage of our Sun's life, its outer atmosphere,
一种会发光的被称作行星状星云的气体
a glowing sphere of gas called a planetary nebula,
将会消失
will have drifted away.
我们一度很强大的太阳仅剩下的
All that will remain of our once powerful star
会是个白热的发光的星体叫做白矮星
will be a glowing white-hot cinder called a white dwarf.
到那时它的体积将会同地球一般大
It will be about the size of the Earth at that point,
克雷格·德福斯特
西南研究院
质量也只有原来的一半
And it'll have about half of its mass remaining.
该星体仍然同原来的太阳一样热
That object still has as much thermal energy as the entire Sun did,
但体积很小且不能像原来一样有效地发出光来
But it's very small and doesn't radiate it very effectively.
白矮星体积小但密度极大
White dwarfs are small but extremely dense.
想象我们太阳成为白矮星后同地球一样大
Imagine our white dwarf Sun as small as the Earth
但质量却和一颗恒星一样
But with the same mass as a whole star.
如果你从白矮星上取下一块
If you were to take a chunk of white dwarf material
手机般大小的物质
the same size as a cell phone,
它会像大象一样重
It would weigh approximately the same
所以说该物质的密度是很大的
as an elephant so it's very dense material
尽管白矮星的体积
Although this white dwarf size
同今天我们所见的太阳相比很小
is very small, relative to the Sun as we know it today.
成为白矮星后
As a white dwarf,
我们的太阳就进入退休阶段了
our Sun will slip into retirement,
消耗它表面积蓄的热量达数十亿
using up its life savings of thermal energy for billions,
甚至数万亿年
even trillions of years.
当它成为一颗白矮星时
When it has become a white dwarf,
它就像是辆沿海岸前行的汽车
It'll be like a car that's coasting.
耗尽汽油后还在行驶
it's run out of gas, but it's still moving
因为它还有热运动能量推到它前进
Because it has energy of motion that's propelling it forward.
它并不会通过燃烧汽油产生新能量
It's not generating any new energy by burning fuel.
而是会将内部储存的能量散发出来
It'll be radiating away the stored energy in its hot interior,
当它年轻有活力时通过核反应
Energy that it had generated through nuclear reactions
产生的能量
when it was young and vibrant.
所以它就像这辆车
So it's like a car
没有汽油还在行驶
that's just going along without any fuel,
直到最后  十分缓慢地停下来
Until finally, eventually, very slowly, it comes to a halt.
在太阳演变成白矮星后
Anything left in the solar system
太阳系中剩下的一切物体
after that transition to the white dwarf stage
都会逐渐冷却下来
would just gradually cool off.
它们仍会围绕白矮星运行
It would remain in orbit around the white dwarf.
运行轨道几乎不会发生变化
The orbital decay times are extremely long,
如同一个冰冷萧索的天体
and it would just stay there
日复一日地在轨道上盘旋
as a quiet, cold orbiting body forever.
成为白矮星的太阳会日益冰冷黯淡
Our white dwarf Sun will become progressively cooler and dimmer.
由于太阳不再产能
Since it's no longer generating energy,
太阳系内的一切都会被冰封
everything in the solar system will begin to freeze.
随着太阳的生命体征逐渐衰弱
As the Sun's vital signs continue to dim,
地球的命运又会如何呢
what will be the forecast for Earth?
日渐年迈的太阳
In its death throes,
临终前也要挣扎一番
our aging Sun will become insufferably hot
首先变成酷热难当的红巨星
as a red giant
随后则是冰冷难耐的白矮星
and then unbearably cold as a white dwarf.
对地球来说  从火到冰的洗礼
This could be the kiss of death for planet Earth
仿佛是与死神来了次拥吻
as it moves from the frying pan and into the frost.
霍莉·吉尔伯特
国家航空航天局戈达航天中心
到太阳成为白矮星的时候
By the time the Sun becomes a white dwarf,
我们可以想象那时地球的温度
we can imagine that temperatures on Earth,
根据它所处于不同的轨道位置
depending on where it is in its orbit,
会以一个惊人的速度显著下降
would drop significantly fairly rapidly
因为白矮星不再通过聚变产能
because the white dwarf is no longer producing energy through fusion
因此  它不再产能供给地球所需的热量
so it's not producing this energy to heat the Earth.
如果地球在太阳红巨星阶段
We'll be fried to a crisp
艾力克斯·菲利潘科
加州大学伯克利分校
保持它的轨道不变  我们就会被热焦
if we remain where we are during the red giant stage,
同样的
but in a similar vein,
如果在白矮星时地球仍处于这个轨道
we will go into a deep freeze
我们就会被冻僵
if we remain where we are when the Sun becomes a white dwarf.
不过  生命在某些区域
Nevertheless, there will be some pockets
仍可以延续下去
where life could continue to survive.
比如  在海洋深处的液态区域
For example, in the liquid parts deep in the oceans,
生命能幸免于难
it could survive.
理论上来说
At the outset,
一开始人类可以住进潜艇
humans could theoretically live in submarines,
在靠近热液火山口的区域生活
near hot hydrothermal vents,
它们能从深处的地核
while they dredge up the geothermal energy
提取地热能
from deep within the Earth's core.
但是一百万年后
But after a million years,
海洋彻冻结底
the oceans would completely freeze
生命不可避免地走向灭亡
and life would inevitably perish.
太阳变成白矮星后
After the Sun becomes a white dwarf,
会越来越冷
it's just gonna cool and cool.
这很像炉子上的锅
It's very much like a pot on the stove.
道格·邓肯
科罗拉多大学
当你关闭了燃嘴  它就失去了能量来源
Once you turn off the burner, there's no more source of energy,
温度逐渐降低  降低  再降低
and so it just gradually gets cooler and cooler and cooler.
如果当太阳仅仅是一颗白矮星的时
If the Earth manages to survive
地球还幸免于难
until the Sun is only a white dwarf star,
那时将很难获取任何能量
it will hardly be getting any energy at all.
我可以十分确信地说
I can say with absolute certainty
如果你活得够长
that if you stick around long enough,
便能经历火的炼狱
you could experience both death by fire
与冰的洗礼
and also death by ice.
失去了太阳释放的能量
Without energy from our Sun,
太阳系幸存的生命都将灰飞烟灭
all remaining life in our solar system will disappear.
然而  我们可以通过目前无法实现的技术
However, this disaster could be preempted
预先阻止这场灾难
by accomplishing what so far has been impossible to do...
那就是在地球上复制太阳的氢聚变反应
actually duplicating the Sun's hydrogen fusion right here on Earth.
控制核聚变的产生与进行已在科学能力所及
Science has already been able to manufacture nuclear fission,
它能使重原子核分裂成更轻更小的轻原子
which involves the splitting of atoms into lighter, smaller nuclei.
正是这股力量驱动了我们的核电站
This is the power that drives our nuclear power plants
并由此激生了核武器
and ignites nuclear weapons.
然而  在太阳核心
But nuclear fusion,
进行的核裂变
which occurs in the core of the Sun,
需要将轻原子聚合生成更大更重的原子核
requires putting nuclei together to form a larger, heavier nucleus.
到目前为止  这项技术还没在地球上实现
And so far, this process has not been achieved here on Earth.
重造一个太阳环境最根本的难点是
The problem with recreating the Sun's conditions
布拉德·海森
加州大学洛城分校
让物质拥有太阳核心处的
is essentially getting materials to the densities
物质密度和温度
and temperatures that you have in the center of the Sun.
太阳自身的引力使压力与密度达到很高的水准
The Sun has its gravity to drive the pressures and densities up,
所以它可以进行这些高级反应
so it can get these high reactions.
在地球上  人类不能奢望利用太阳的引力
On Earth, we don't have the luxury of using the Sun's gravity,
因此  我们必须找到其它方法试着压缩物质
so we have to find other ways to try and compress the material
从而产生足够大的密度
and generate the kinds of densities that you see.
在加州北部的劳伦斯利弗莫尔国家实验室中
At the Lawrence Livmore national laboratory in northern California,
科学家们正进行一次挑战
scientists are taking on the challenge
他们试图创造一颗微缩人造恒星
by attempting to create a miniature man-made star.
这项实验包括将有三个足球场大小的
The experiment involves aiming the world's largest laser...
世界上规模最大的激光器
the size of three football fields...
瞄准一个满载氢燃料的BB子弹大小的目标
at a BB-sized target filled with hydrogen fuel.
在一个惯性约束实验中
In an inertial confinement experiment
就像劳伦斯利弗莫尔的这次实验
like the one at Lawrence Livermore,
你需要一颗小圆球
you start with a small pellet,
它的直径大概有半英寸
maybe a half an inch across,
中心填充着固体材料
the core of which is made of a solid material
由聚变所需的氢组成
containing lots of hydrogen to undergo fusion.
外层包裹着几层不同的材料
The outside of which has layers of different material
克雷格·德福斯特
西南研究院
这种设计使它们能产生冲击波
that are engineered to produce a shock wave
尽可能地进入并挤压内核
that will drive in and compress that core as much as possible.
强激光束将散射成192小束
The colossal laser will split into 192 separate beams
轰击舱内的小球
that will strike the pellet housed inside a capsule.
当燃料丸的外壳接触到高能X射线
When the fuel pellet's shell is struck by these high energy x-rays,
便会发生爆炸
it should implode
最终  在核内产生核聚变反应
and then ultimately produce nuclear fusion in its core.
如果我们掌握了可控廉价的核聚变技术
If we had controlled, affordable nuclear fusion,
它将改变一切
it would change everything.
我们生活的方方面面都将变得不同
Many things about our lives would change.
最重要的是  我们将不再需要太阳
But most importantly, we wouldn't need the Sun anymore.
我们能随心所欲地生产能量  热量和光
We could produce energy, heat, light on demand.
有了氢的供给  便能生产我们所需的能量
We could live anywhere in the cosmos
人类便能立足于宇宙的任何一个角落
with a supply of hydrogen and make our own energy.
我们可以迅速飞往其它行星
We could fly to other planets very quickly,
只用几天时间  而不再是几年
in days instead of years.
你几乎可以从任何含有氢氧元素的物质中
You can extract all the water you need from practically any material
提取所需的水
that contains hydrogen and oxygen.
如果周围没有充足的氧气  你可以自己生产
If there isn't enough oxygen around, you could make some.
产生稳定的核聚变
Generating reliable nuclear fusion could
将消除我们对太阳的依赖
ultimately save Earth and all forms of life
并最终拯救地球和所有的生命
by eliminating our dependence on the Sun.
然而  太阳自身的命运却已注定
Yet the Sun's own fate is forever sealed.
那就是成为一颗日益黯淡阴冷的白矮星
As a white dwarf, it will become dimmer and cooler.
这颗曾经为整个太阳系提供能量的恒星
The star that once provided energy to an entire solar system
终将从人们的视野中淡去
will eventually fade from sight.
当太阳最终冷却到一定程度
When the Sun eventually cools off so much,
它甚至无法被你的肉眼观测到
you won't even be able to see it with your eyes.
这也是为什么有些人称它为黑矮星
And so that's why some people call it a black dwarf
或暗恒星
or a dark star.
它无影于无形  静止于太空  流传于永恒
It'll just be invisible, sitting there in space nearly forever.
在五十亿年里  太阳系将注定迎来它的末日
Our solar system cannot dodge its date with doom in 5 billion years.
但一个星系的终结
But the death of one planetary system
能唤起另一个星系的新生
can spark the birth of another.
太阳的星云最终将和
Our Sun's nebula will eventually blend together
其它星际物质交融
with other stellar material
孕育出下一代恒星
and spawn the next generation of stars.
也许在它的呵护下
And one might even nurture
另一个生机勃勃的地球终将出现
another vibrant planet like Earth.